Guide to the William Golden Papers, 1911-1970 RL.11001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Golden papers
1911-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Golden, William
RL.11001
15 Linear Feet
Graphic artist and Creative Director at CBS Radio and Television divisions. Creator of the CBS "eye" logo and corporate typography.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Advertising and Design; Advertising; CBS Corporate Files; Personal Files; Publications and printed materials; and Large Format Materials.
Biographical note
Chronology
1911 Born, Manhattan, N.Y.
1928 Graduates from Vocational School for Boys; moves to Los Angeles and works in lithography and photoengraving.
1930s Returns to New York; works for Journal American, House & Garden
1937 CBS Radio, Promotion Department
1940 Art Director, CBS Radio
1941 Office of War Information
1943-1946 U.S. Army; works on training manual design; discharged 1946 with rank of Captain
1946 CBS Television; named Creative Director in 1951
1951 New corporate style for CBS: typography based on Didot typeface; "eye" logo symbol based on imaged from Shaker folk art
1959 Dies, New York
Provenance
The William Golden Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2014
Collection Overview
Primarily print advertisements, pamphlets and brochures, corporate publications and other printed materials, personal correspondence, design work and other materials that document Golden's career in advertising and graphic design at CBS Radio and Television. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Separated Materials
A run of the serial publication "CBS Program Book" followed by "CBS Television Clients and Programs" has been removed and cataloged separately.
Commercial art; Radio advertising; Graphic arts; Commercial artists -- United States; Commercial artists; Radio advertising -- United States; Television advertising; Television advertising -- United States; Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc.; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
- Advertising and Design, 1951-1959; 1
  - Advertising and Direct Mail (annual compilation), 1951-1956; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Advertising and Direct Mail (annual compilation), 1957-1959; 4 folders (Box 2)
- Advertising--Pamphlets and folders (Radio), 1941-1958; undated; 2
  - 29,300,000 Families Move Less than an Inch, 1941 (Box 3)
  - 24 Hours a Day, undated (Box 3)
  - A Clean Sweep for a New Broom (Lorenz Broom/Housewives Protective League), undated (Box 3)
  - A Good Practice, 1952 (Box 3)
  - After a Tough Trial, 1958 (Box 3)
  - After Being First by 57%, undated (Box 3)
  - An 18.2 Hooper (rating), 1948 (Box 3)
  - An Inch That's Worth 4,000,000 Impressions, 1947 (Box 3)
  - CBS station display kit, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Don't Let 'Em Get Away, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Hard to Keep Up With, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Here's a Sales Counter, undated (Box 3)
  - If It's the Biggest You Want, undated (Box 3)
  - It's Easy Listening, Too (The Missus Goes A-Shopping), undated (Box 3)
  - No Matter How You Look at It, undated (Box 3)
  - No Time for Women?, undated (Box 3)
  - On February 19 We'll Be There, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Radio's Margaret Arlen, undated (Box 3)
  - Rip Off the Mask!, undated (Box 3)
  - Steady As She Goes (WEEI), undated (Box 3)
  - Take It or Leave It (Eversharp pens and pencils), undated (Box 3)
  - The Free Company Presents, undated (Box 3)
  - The Main Attraction, 1949 (Box 3)
  - The Second Most Important Thing in Radio, circa 1947 (Box 3)
  - The Story of a Suntan Lotion Manufacturer, undated (Box 3)
  - To Be Continued (Programming guide), undated (Box 3)
  - Try WBT for Size!, 1950 (Box 3)
  - Two Letters that Took 10 Years to Write, undated (Box 3)
  - WBT Has a Good Time, undated (Box 3)
  - WBT Now Reaches a Market, 1950 (Box 3)
  - What's Been Hot in Chicago All Summer?, undated (Box 3)
  - Yeah, But Can He Lift a Sales Curve? (series), undated (Box 4)
- Advertising--Pamphlets and folders (Television), 1946-1958; undated; 3
  - Better Late than Ever, undated (Box 4)
  - How to Keep Film Ratings Up, undated (Box 4)
  - Momentum, 1948 (Box 4)
  - No Place to Hide, undated (Box 4)
  - Prewar vs. Postwar Television, circa 1946 (Box 4)
  - Primer for Prophets, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Programs for Profit, undated (Box 4)
  - Speaking of Clippings, undated (Box 4)
  - Sure, Television's Amazing (series), undated (Box 4)
  - Television reference guide, undated (Box 4)
  - The Motive is Money, undated (Box 4)
  - The People's Choice, undated (Box 4)
  - They'll Be Just, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Things Look Good on WCBS-TV, undated (Box 4)
  - We've got 26 Big Stars, undated (Box 4)
  - Women!, undated (Box 4)
  - You Ought to Be in Pictures (TV Film Sales), undated (Box 4)
- Advertising--Print, 1950-1957; undated; 4
  - Print advertisements, 1950-1956; undated; 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Print advertisements--Insertion schedules, 1952-1957 (Box 4)
  - Print advertisements--Photographs, undated (Box 4)
  - Design--Letterhead, stationery, etc., 1956-1967; undated; 10 folders (Box 5)
- CBS Corporate Files, 1939-1967; undated; 5
  - Administsrative directory, undated (Box 6)
  - CBS Annual Report, 1956 (Box 6)
  - CBS film reel labels, undated (Box 6)
  - How to Be a Good Right Arm: Practical Hints for Secretaries, undated (Box 6)
  - Merry Christmas, Frank Stanton, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1956-1967; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Press releases, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Rate cards, 1942-1959 (Box 6)
  - Stockholder literature, 1939-1964; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - The Company You Keep (personnel guidelines), 1958 (Box 6)
- Personal Files, 1911-1970; undated; 6
  - Awards and notices, 1959-1970; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Birth, death certificates, 1911; 1959 (Box 7)
  - Business correspondence, 1939-1963 (Box 7)
  - CBS Reports (transcript of interview with William Golden), 1960 (Box 7)
  - CBS stock, pension records, 1942-1959 (Box 7)
  - Certificate of Deposite, Bail Fund of the Civil Rights Congress of New York, 1949 (Box 7)
  - Exhibit materials, 1962-1964; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Legal correspondence, 1949-1961 (Box 7)
  - Memorial/Tributes, 1959-1966; undated; 6 folders (Box 7)
  - Military service, 1942-1950 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1963-1965; undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Personal correspondence, 1949-1959; undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Photographs, undated, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Subversive organization declaration, signed with explanation by William Golden, 1950 (Box 8)
  - Wartime correspondence, 1942-1946; undated; 19 folders (Box 8)
  - Writings, undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
- Publications and Printed Materials, 1938-1962; undated; 7
  - AIGA Journal, Vol. IV no. 1-2, includes article "The Golden Touch" by Fritz Eichenberg, undated (Box 9)
  - Almanack: A New Quarterly Almanack, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Almanack: The CBS Almanack for Radio Program Makers, 1938 (Box 9)
  - America's Greatest Sales Vehicle, 1956 (Box 9)
  - An Analysis of Senator John W. Bricker's Report Entitled "The Network Monopoly,", 1956 (Box 9)
  - Archibald Macleish, William Paley, Edward R. Murrow: In Honor of a Man and an Idea, 1941 (Box 9)
  - Arthur Hull Hayes, Radio and Education, 1957 (Box 9)
  - At Year's End, 1956 (Box 9)
  - CBS American School on the Air, 1947 (Box 9)
  - CBS Demonstrates Full Color Television in the Radar Frequencies, 1945 (Box 9)
  - CBS Newsfilm, undated (Box 9)
  - Charges for Facilities and Production Services, 1952 (Box 9)
  - Close-Up: A Picture of the Men and Methods that Make CBS Television, 1949; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Columbia Square, undated (Box 9)
  - Columbia's RFD (Rural Free Delivery) Audience, 1938 (Box 9)
  - Contents: 24 Hours, 1954 (Box 10)
  - Davidson Taylor, Frances Morehouse: A March and a Dance (Letters to the New York Times), 1942 (Box 10)
  - Follow-Up: How Creative Production Translated a Point of View about Television into an Important Success Story, 1948 (Box 10)
  - Free Television and the American People, undated (Box 10)
  - Forecast (series), 1940 (Box 10)
  - Forecasts in FM and Television, 1945 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, Broadcasting in 1973, 1948 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, CBS Now and Tomorrow, 1954 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, Christian Science Monitor reprints, 1956 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, Color Television--The Way Ahead (FCC), 1946 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, Journalism by Slide Rule?, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, Press conference, 1948 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, Television and People, undated (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, testimony before Senate, 1954-1956 (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, The People Must Know, undated (Box 10)
  - Frank Stanton, You and Television, 1948 (Box 10)
  - Henry Pringle, Guard It, Cherish It, and Work for It, 1941 (Box 10)
  - J.L. Van Volkenburg, Key to an Expanding Economy, 1955 (Box 10)
  - J.L. Van Volkenburg, Television's Impact on American Business, 1952 (Box 10)
  - J.L. Van Volkenburg, The Structure of Television, 1949 (Box 10)
  - Kenneth Franklin, Broadcast Journalism in an ICBM Age, 1957 (Box 10)
  - L. Fritz Gruber, Radio Advertising (from Graphis, in English, French and German), 1949 (Box 10)
  - Long Shot: How a Network's Responsibility for Its Program Schedule Serves Its Audience, Its Advertisers, and Its Affiliated Stations, circa 1958 (Box 11)
  - Louis Cowan, Television and the Arts, 1959 (Box 11)
  - Mark Van Doren, Invitation to Learning, 1941 (Box 11)
  - Memorandum Concerning the Statement of Richard A. Moore, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Merle S. Jones, The Future of Television is in Your Hands, 1959 (Box 11)
  - Merle S. Jones, The Multiple Target of Industrial Advertising, 1957 (Box 11)
  - Mid-Century, 1950 (Box 11)
  - More Than Meets the Eye, undated (Box 11)
  - Neither Free Nor Equal (WCCO series on discrimination), 1947 (Box 11)
  - Network Practices, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Open End with David Susskind, Jack Gould, Pat Weaver, 1959 (Box 11)
  - Opinion of Counsel and Memorandum Concerning the Applicability of Antritrust Laws to the Television Broadcast Activities of Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc., 1956 (Box 11)
  - Print: The Corporate Image Edition, 1958 (Box 11)
  - Richard Hubbell, Television Programming and Production, 1945 (Box 12)
  - Richard Salant, Statement to House Committee, 1956 (Box 12)
  - School of the Air of the Americas, 1942-1943 (Box 12)
  - Seems Radio is Here to Stay, 1949 (Box 12)
  - Seventh Son--On Monday Nights at Nine, 1941 (Box 12)
  - Sig Mickelson, Television and Public Enlightenment in a Free Society, 1959 (Box 12)
  - Sig Mickelson, Television and the Church, 1956 (Box 12)
  - Studio News, undated (Box 12)
  - Sunrise Semester, undated (Box 12)
  - Tags (a profile of U.S. Army Company G), undated (Box 12)
  - Television Audience Research, 1945 (Box 12)
  - Television Network (articles), 1956 (Box 12)
  - The Actors Present "War,", 1940 (Box 12)
  - The Face of Red China, 1958 (Box 12)
  - The Paul W. Kesten Fellowship in Advertising and Marketing (Harvard Business School), 1957 (Box 12)
  - The Press and the People (series), undated (Box 13)
  - The Sound of Your Life: A Record of Radio's First Generation, 1950 (Box 13)
  - The Unique Baby, undated (Box 13)
  - The Vice Presidency, 1955 (Box 13)
  - Cipes Pineles Golden, Kurt Weihs, Robert Strunsky: The Visual Craft of William Golden, 1962 (Box 13)
  - The World of Sholom Aleichem, undated (Box 13)
  - U.S. Television Ownership by Counties, 1953 (Box 13)
  - What Makes It Tick? (radio and automobiles), 1941 (Box 13)
  - Who's Who in Boston (Past and Present), undated (Box 13)
  - William Gittinger, Seems Radio is Here to Stay, 1949 (Box 13)
  - William Paley, Radio and Its Critics, 1948 (Box 13)
  - William Paley, Testimony Before House Committee, 1942 (Box 13)
  - Years of Crisis: Where We Stand, 1957-1958 (Box 13)
  - You and Alcohol, 1946-1947 (Box 13)
- Large Format Materials, 1938-1964; undated; 8
  - Advertisements--CBS Radio Sales, 1947-1951 (Box 14)
  - Advertisements--CBS Television Film Sales, undated (Box 14)
  - Advertisements--CBS Television Spot Sales, 1953-1954 (Box 14)
  - Advertisements--Mid-America Re-Elects a Favorite Son (KMOX), 1948 (Box 14)
  - Advertisements--WABC Inauguration, 1941 (Box 14)
  - Awards--American Instutite of Graphic Arts (AIGA), 1950-1953; 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Awards--Direct Mail Advertising Association (DMAA), 1947-1950 (Box 14)
  - Personal--Miscellaneous notes, 1959 (Box 14)
  - Publication--All Those in Favor (CBS full network promotion), 1942 (Box 14)
  - Publication--Color television promotion, circa 1940s (Box 14)
  - Publication--Dealer's Choice, circa 1953 (Box 14)
  - Publication--Eye Opener: CBS Television Programming Promotion, 1953-1954 (Box 14)
  - Publication--Films for Television, 1953 (Box 14)
  - Publication--It Takes All Three to Catch Customers, undated (Box 14)
  - Publication--Radio Goes to College, 1938; 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Publication--Radio Sales, 1947 (Box 14)
  - Publication--Reading Between the Lines (John Crosby, Chicago), 1948 (Box 14)
  - Publication--Roper Counts Customers, circa 1940 (Box 14)
  - Publication--The Power Behind the Screen, undated (Box 14)
  - Publication--The Story of Sex on the Air in Boston, 1947 (Box 14)
  - Advertisements, radio and television, 1938-1954; undated; 3 folders (Box 15)
  - Design--Mr. Lookit, undated (Box 15)
  - Personal--Insurance, property and estate documents, 1945-1960 (Box 15)
  - Photographs--Elijah D. Clark Jr. High School, undated (Box 15)
  - Photographs--Military service, 1940s (Box 15)
  - Photographs--Miscellaneous, 1952; undated (Box 15)
  - Publication--ADLA News, 1959 Oct. (Box 15)
  - Publication--August is Bigger than Illinois, 1940 (Box 15)
  - Publication--CBS Sweeps All Network Firsts in 1940 (Box 15)
  - Publication--Here Are the Facts, 1947 (Box 15)
  - Publication--La Cinematographie Francaise (serial, in French), 1938-1946 (Box 15)
  - Publication--Sports from Columbia, 1938 (Box 15)
  - Publication--Strength--Where It Counts Most (CBS advertising presentation), circa 1949 (Box 15)
  - Advertisements, laminated, 1953; undated (Box 16)
  - Advertisements, radio, 1938-1951; 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Advertisements, television, 1948-1959; undated; 10 folders (Box 16)
  - Advertisements, laminated, undated, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Advertisements, radio, 1940-1951; undated; 7 folders (Box 17)
  - Advertisements, television, 1950-1959; undated; 8 folders (Box 18)
  - Advertisements, television, Harvest, 1955 (Box 18)
  - Advertisements, television, The Magic is Built In (children and television), undated (Box 18)
  - Advertisements, television, This Is a House (children and television), undated (Box 18)
  - Advertisements, television, Which Way In?, 1954 (Box 18)
  - Awards, American Institute of Graphi Arts (AIGA), 1948-1960; 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Awards, Art Directors Club, 1942-1959; 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Awards, Lithograhers National Association, 1955-1956 (Box 19)
  - Awards, New York Employing Printers Association, 1958 (Box 19)
  - Awards, Photo-Engraving Board of Trade of New York, 1959 (Box 19)
  - Designs--logos, images, stationery, etc., undated, 5 folders (Box 19)
  - Publication--Crescendo: A Chronicle of Radio's Unique Power to Move People to Direct Action, 1947 (Box 19)
  - Publication--My Eye, by William Golden, undated (Box 19)
  - Publication--You Know What You Want, 1948 (Box 19)
  - Advertisements, laminated, undated, 4 folders (Box 20)
  - Advertisements, radio, undated, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Advertisements, television, undated, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Advertisements, radio and television, newspaper (fragile), undated, 6 folders (Box 21)
  - Awards--Art Directors Club, AIGA, New York Employing Printers, 1949-1958 (Box 21)
  - Storyboards and notes, undated (Box 21)
  - Three-dimensional: CBS "Eye" logo coasters, undated (Box 22)
  - Three-dimensional: Gold medallion, Art Directors Club Award for Special Merit, undated (Box 22)
  - Three-dimensional: Society of Typographic Arts Award for Outstanding Achievement in Trademark Design, 1964 (Box 22)
  - Three-dimensional: Charlemane the Lion hand puppet from The Morning Show, circa 1954 (Box 23)
  - Three-dimensional: samples of cloth with CBS "eye" logo, undated (Box 23)
  - Posters from exhibit "The Visual Craft of William Golden", 1962 (Oversize-folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes the CBS "eye" logo; preface by Frank Stanton from the Cipe Pineles book The Visual Craft of William Golden